So this is where I left you looking at this satisfying chart on training loss and seeing the training
여기서 제가 여러분께 훈련 손실에 대한 만족스러운 차트를 보여드렸는데요 훈련 손실에
loss coming down.
대한 차트를요
Could stare at this all day.
종일 봐도 안 질리겠어요
Uh, but, uh, we will move on to other charts.
다른 차트로 넘어가도록 하죠
Uh, let's go back to this diagram again.
이 도표를 다시 보죠
Um, I wanted to point out this one that you may have already seen.
이미 보셨을 수도 있는 이 사진을 보여드릴게요
This is the learning rate.
이게 학습률이에요
Let's blow this up.
날려 버리죠
Uh, so this is showing you exactly what I was trying to describe earlier, but but as I, as I told
이게 제가 아까 설명하려고 했던 바로 그 모습이에요 하지만 제가 말씀드렸듯이
you it would, it looks much more clear when when you're looking at it, uh, in weights and biases.
무게와 편향으로 보면 훨씬 더 명확해 보이죠
Um, so this is showing how the learning rate changed over time from the beginning through to the end
이건 지난 네 번의 시대를 거치며 학습률이 어떻게 변했는지 보여줍니다.
of the four, almost four, uh, didn't quite get to the end of the fourth epoch, um, when I ran the
거의 네 번째 시대까지 학습률이 변하지 않았죠. 이전의 모형을 실행했을 때요.
And what you can see is that the learning rate started at zero.
보시다시피 학습률은 0에서 시작됐죠
It then went up, uh, because of the warm up to this point here.
그 후 상승했죠 이 지점까지 온난화 때문에요
Um, and then you can see that it, it gradually comes down in this very nice, smooth way, slowly
그러면 이렇게 매끈하게 조금씩 내려오는 게 보이죠 처음엔 천천히 시작하지만 점점
to start with and then a lot more.
더 많이 내려와요
And then at the end it tails off.
그러다 끝에 가서는 꼬리가 떨어져요
And the idea is that it actually gets to exactly zero when you're four epochs are up.
네 개의 개혁이 끝나면 정확히 0까지 올라가요
But I didn't make it to the end of the fourth epoch.
하지만 네 번째 시대까지 못 버텼어요
And obviously if you choose to run for one epoch, then you get this whole chart just for the one epoch.
한 시대의 작업을 실행하면 하나의 작업에만 전체 차트가 생겨요.
It just takes the number of epochs that you set, and it smoothens the learning rate over that number
몇 개의 폭동을 일으켰는지를 알면 학습 속도가 빨라져요.
Uh, so, um, it hopefully illustrates exactly the point.
그 요점을 잘 보여주는 것 같아요
And you can see that our blue line representing the current batch is right up at the top of this.
현재 배치를 나타내는 파란 선이 이 위에 있는 게 보이시죠
Uh, and it looked flat to us only because we were at the very, very top.
우리가 제일 꼭대기에 있어서 밋밋해 보였던 거예요
But in due course, it is going to come down smoothly, just as its predecessor did.
하지만 때가 되면 전임자처럼 순조롭게 내려올 거예요
Uh, so then another thing I wanted to mention, um, is that when we were looking at the different
말씀드리고 싶은 다른 것은 여기 여러 개의 실행을 살펴볼 때 이 아이콘을
runs just here, you can see you can use this eye icon here to decide what you're going to be looking
사용할 수 있습니다 무엇을 볼 것인지 결정하기 위해서요
at.
여기 이 중간에 있는 건 미처 못 봤어요 Put it up Put it
Now, what this is, is that after my, uh, my this batch, uh, was a brutally kicked off by by kicked
이게 뭐냐면요 제가 만든 건 구글이 잔인하게 인스턴스를 차단했어요
I was annoyed and decided I wanted to try and continue where it left off and run another couple of epochs.
짜증이 나서 하던 일을 계속하고 다른 시대를 개척하기로 했죠
Even though the results got worse, I wanted to see what happened.
결과는 나빠졌지만 어떻게 됐는지 보고 싶었어요
I wanted to take it to an extreme, and I wanted to make sure it wasn't just an anomaly that the fourth
전 그걸 극단으로 몰고 가서 네 번째 시대에서 결과가 나빠진 변칙적인
epoch, the results got worse.
사례가 아니길 바랐어요
Maybe the fifth epoch, they would suddenly be a lot better.
다섯 번째 시대에는 훨씬 더 좋아질지도 몰라요
So I at least wanted to see it play out a bit.
그래서 적어도 비트가 어떻게 되는지 보고 싶었어요
Um, and so I'm going to now show that for you.
이제 그걸 보여 드릴게요
Now it's going to be a bit confusing because I started it again.
좀 헷갈릴 거예요 비트를 다시 시작했거든요
It's not going to continue off to the right here.
오른쪽으로는 안 이어져요
It's going to begin over on the left.
왼쪽에서 시작할 거예요
So you just have to bear in mind that it's going to see it as if it was the first training step.
첫 번째 훈련 단계처럼 보일 거라는 걸 명심하세요
But in fact, what I'm going to show you belongs over to the right of this purple line.
하지만 제가 보여드릴 것은 이 보라색 선 오른쪽에 있는 거예요
Let's see.
어디 보죠
Now this this this thing.
이건 말이죠
And there it is.
저기 있네요
So let me blow this up.
확대해 볼게요
So hopefully it's clear to you that there should really be over here.
그러니 여기 있어야 한다는 걸 확실히 아셨으면 좋겠네요
It should be we should be able to take that and pull it over to the right.
저걸 잡아서 오른쪽으로 당길 수 있어야 해요
Because this is what happened when I resumed that SFT trainer from where it left off down here.
왜냐하면 제가 여기서 훈련을 다시 시작했을 때 일어난 일이거든요
And what you can see is this is then basically a fifth, another full epoch, um, representing that
여기 보이는 게 다섯 번째이자 다른 완전한 시대예요 네 번째 시대를 끝내지 못한 거죠
we never completed the fourth one, but this is like doing a whole nother epoch.
이건 완전히 다른 시대예요
And then this would be like the whole of the sixth epoch.
그럼 여섯 번째 이화기가 완성되는 거죠
Um, and what you can see again, another of these falls between the, um, when it, when it started,
다시 한번 말씀드리자면 6번째 시대가 시작된 시기와는 확실히 다른
uh, the sixth epoch and at this point, definitely in a very suspicious territory.
점이 있습니다 이 시점에서는 확실히 의심스러운 상황이 벌어지고 있죠
The loss looking too low.
손실이 너무 적어요
And sure enough, when I took these versions of the model and tried to run tests against them, they
아니나 다를까 이 모델들을 가지고 테스트를 해 봤더니 제가 가져온
were all poorer in performance than the model that I took from a cut off about about here.
모델보다 성능이 떨어졌죠 이쯤에서 잘라낸 모델보다요
So it was a test worth doing.
해볼 만한 실험이었어요
I needed to satisfy myself that it wasn't just bad luck back here, but that it really was overfitting
저 자신을 만족시켜야 했어요 운이 나빴던 게 아니라 너무 과했던 거고 더는 유용한
and that I wasn't getting useful results anymore.
결과를 얻지 못한다는 걸요
And that did prove to be the case.
실제로도 그런 경우였고요
So it was a good test to do.
좋은 시험이 됐어요
And you can benefit from this because you can know if you have decided to do the full, the full Monty
이로써 이득을 볼 수 있습니다 풀 몬티로 대규모
and run with this big version of the model, then, you know, once you've done, uh, your you might
버전을 실행하기로 결정했다면 세 개 개혁을 넘어선 안 되니까요
There is no no use for that, in my experience, unless you've tried changing hyperparameters and you've
제 경험상 그건 소용이 없어요 hyperperameter를 변경해 보고 뭔가 다른 걸 발견하지
discovered something different.
않는 한은요
Uh, so then, um, the final thing I'll show you, you can play around with many of the other charts
마지막으로 보여드릴 것은 다른 도표와 무게, 편향 등을 가지고 놀아보실 수
and weights and biases.
있어요
There's lots to explore.
탐험할 게 많아요
You can look at the gradients themselves, and that is quite a rabbit hole.
경사만 봐도 알 수 있는데 정말 혼란스러워요
And you'd have to do a little bit of, uh, digging and research to understand what you're looking at
비트 박스를 조사하고 조사해야 해요 뭘 보고 있는지 이해하고 거기서 뭘 배울
and how to learn things from it.
수 있는지 알려면요
And ideally, what you the main things that you want to be looking for is making sure that you never
이상적으로 여러분이 가장 중요하게 여기는 건 Get 절차가
get into a situation where your gradients are becoming zero.
0이 되는 상황은 절대 없도록 하는 거예요
Um, which means that you're not learning anymore.
더는 배우는 게 없다는 뜻이죠
If your gradients are zero, then your model is no longer learning and there's no use to be continuing
그러데이션이 0이면 모델은 더 이상 학습할 수 없고 학습 과정을 계속할
the learning process.
필요가 없어요
So you want to watch out for gradients being zero, and you also want to watch out for gradients blowing
그러데이션이 0이 되지 않도록 주의해야 합니다 그러데이션이
up and being too high, because that means that your your model is going to be bouncing around too much
너무 높거나 커지는 것도 주의해야 합니다 그렇게 되면 여러분의 모델이 너무 많이 흔들릴 테니까요
unless your learning rate is really tiny.
학습률이 아주 낮지 않다면요
Uh, your model is going to be, uh, not learning in a productive way.
이 모델은 비생산적으로 학습할 거예요
So those are some of the things to look for when you're looking at gradients in weights and biases.
무게나 우회도로 그라데이션을 볼 때는 이런 점을 주의 깊게 봐야 해요
But the last thing I wanted to show you was going to hugging face.
하지만 얼굴 껴안는 건 보여 주고 싶지 않았어요
Um, and just show you if you if you remember this, this model here, which is the, uh, the the version
혹시 기억하실지 모르겠지만 이 모델을 보여드릴게요 제가 모든 시대를 위해 실행했던
of the Pricer model that I ran for all of these epochs.
프라이서 모델의 버전이에요
Um, you see this?
이거 보여요?
The name of the run is the name that I constructed based on the date and time.
실행 이름은 날짜와 시간에 근거해 제가 만든 이름이에요
Um, and it ends in, uh, 39.
39년으로 끝나죠
The number of seconds.
초의 개수죠
Uh, just keep keep that in your mind.
그 점을 명심하세요
When we turn to hugging face, you go to the avatar menu and to your own name.
포옹하는 얼굴이 나오면 아바타 메뉴로 가서 본인 이름을 누르세요
Uh, you will then see your spaces if you have any, your models and your data sets.
모델과 데이터 집합이 있다면 공간을 확인할 수 있어요
You can see I have 1 or 2.
1, 2개 있는 거 보이시죠?
Uh, and when it comes to Pricer, I've run this once or twice.
프라이서에 관해서는 한두 번 실행해 봤어요
Uh, uh, and these, each of these represent the different repos that represent one of the different
이 표시는 각각 다른 회수 건과 다른 가격대 거래 건을
pricer runs.
나타내요
Um, and I like to keep them each each of these runs as a separate repo so that I can have all the different
전 각각의 압류 프로그램을 따로 보관해요 이 압류 프로그램 안에서
epochs and everything within this, this, this one repo.
다양한 시대를 경험할 수 있게요
So what this 139 I think is the one that was the big guy with, with the, the, the four, three and
139개국이라는 건 큰 인물이 네 번인가 세 번 반을 폭동한
a half epochs.
거겠군요
So if we click into this, um, it comes up with the model page, uh, and if you go to files and versions,
이걸 클릭하면 모델 페이지가 뜨는데요 파일과 버전으로 가보면 기본적으로 Git을 보고
what you're looking at here is basically you're looking at git, you're looking at a repo which has
있는 겁니다 회수 깃을 보고 있는데 모델과 관련된 파일이
within it the files associated with your model.
그 안에 있는 거죠
Um, and as I mentioned uh, recently, you can see that the business here is this file, the safe tensors.
그리고 말씀드린 것처럼 최근에 이 사업은 이 안전한 텐서 파일인 걸 보실 수 있어요
And that file is 109MB, which is the size of the adapters that the adapters that we're using with are
그 파일은 109MB로 우리가 함께 사용하는 어댑터의 크기죠 32로 설정된 어댑터요
When we did the maths, we worked out that that would be 109MB worth of weights.
계산을 해보니 109MB의 무게가 나오더군요
And that is all in this file.
이 파일에 다 있어요
Safe tenses right here.
여기가 안전해요
Um, and, um, yeah, there's there's, uh, a few other things that we could look at.
그리고 몇 가지 다른 것도 살펴볼 수 있어요
Adaptive config.json, uh, gives information about the, the adapter that we're using for the Lora
Adaptive config요 json은 로라 미세 조정에 사용하는 어댑터에 관한 정보를 제공해요
And you can see, for example, it has the target modules stored in here, and it has our value of R
예를 들어 여기에 저장된 대상 모듈이 있고 R32 값을 가지고
32.
있어요
It says we're using Lora training.
로라의 훈련을 이용한다고 쓰여 있어요
Um, and so it has and it has the base model name uh llama 3.18 billion in there.
기본 모델 이름이 llama 3이에요 180억 달러요
Um, so that that gives you a sense of all of the information that's saved for this, this model.
이 모델을 위해 저장된 모든 정보를 알 수 있죠
But the other thing I wanted to point out was this 16 commits over here.
또 하나 지적하고 싶은 건 16이 커밋하는 거예요
So this is showing the commit history.
커밋의 역사를 보여주네요
And basically every 5000 steps, um, the code that you saw was saving.
기본적으로 5천 걸음마다 코드를 절약하는 거예요
This was pushing our model to the hub.
우리 모델을 중심으로 밀어냈어요
That was something we configured in the training parameters.
훈련 매개 변수에서 설정된 거예요
So it was being saved every 5000 steps.
5천 걸음마다 절약했어요
And that means that we can load in any of these models and test them.
이 모델 중 어떤 것이든 로드해 테스트할 수 있다는 거죠
And that's how we can select the one that's performing the best.
그렇게 해서 가장 뛰어난 선수를 뽑을 수 있어요
We've got each of these different checkpoints.
체크포인트가 각각 달라요
And we can do as many of these as we want.
이런 건 얼마든지 할 수 있어요
Um, and uh, and we can use that to, to, to come back and recreate that moment when the model was
그 경험을 바탕으로 모델이 훈련받던 그 순간을 다시 재현할
at that point in training.
수 있어요
Um, and so you can imagine I could have all of my different training runs all in this as different,
제가 다양한 훈련을 할 수 있다고 상상해보세요. 이 모든
uh, different revisions of this, uh, different, different versions of this price, the repository.
것이, 어... 이 가격의 다른 버전의 다른 수정본, 저장소에서요.
But then it would get very cluttered.
Get it 하면 어수선해져요
And that's why I separate it out so that each run is its own repo.
그래서 각각의 주행은 따로 회수하도록 구분했어요
And then the different batch steps show here, um, as the different history of the commits.
다른 배치 단계가 여기 있습니다 커밋의 다른 히스토리인데요
Um, I think that's a nice, organized way of doing it.
그게 멋지고 체계적인 방법 같아요
So that's how to see the model in the in the Huggingface hub.
이게 H깅페이스 허브에서 모델을 보는 방법이에요
Uh, presumably We'll see.
두고 봐야죠
This is the one that's running right now.
지금 작동 중인 거예요
It's updated 15 minutes ago.
15분 전에 업데이트됐어요
So we go into this go into files and versions.
파일과 버전으로 가 볼게요
We'll see that.
두고 보죠
Yes it's already saved a version.
네, 이미 버전이 저장됐어요
We've got to step 5000.
5000단계를 해야 해요
So one version of this or two commits because there was an initial commit.
이것의 한 버전 혹은 두 버전은 커밋합니다 초기 커밋이 있으니까요
And then step 5000 is just has been saved 15 minutes ago.
5000단계는 15분 전에 해결되었어요
So there's already a model that's running.
이미 실행 중인 모델이 있는 거죠
And if you've been doing this at the same time as me, then you'll be in a similar boat and you'll be
저와 같은 시기에 이 일을 해왔다면 여러분도 저와 같은 처지일
having versions of this model being uploaded to the Huggingface hub while I speak.
겁니다 제가 말하는 동안 이 모델의 버전을 허깅페이스 허브에 업로드하겠죠
And you'll actually, you would be able to test them right away.
바로 테스트할 수 있어요
You don't need to wait for the training to complete.
훈련이 끝날 때까지 기다릴 필요 없어요
Um, so there we go.
자, 됐어요
We've seen the, uh, the training underway, with the losses showing here that are a bit hard to understand.
비트가 훈련하는 걸 봤는데 여기서 보이는 패배는 이해하기 좀 어렵네요
We visualize them beautifully in weights and biases, and we've seen the model itself being saved to
무게와 편향으로 아름답게 그려졌고 모델 자체가 중심에 저장되는 것도 봤어요
And this is the experience of training.
이건 훈련의 경험이에요
And I tell you, I can do this for hours.
몇 시간이고 할 수 있어요
And I have done this for hours, which is very tragic of me.
몇 시간 동안이나 이러고 있었어요 정말 비극적이죠
And in fact, I mentioned, I think right back at the very beginning of this course, that that screen
사실 이 코스가 시작될 때 말씀드린 것 같은데
you see over there that actually has weights and biases on it and the the chart that I was just showing
저기 보이는 화면에 무게와 편향성이 있습니다 그리고 방금
you, uh, was, uh, this chart was the chart that was on there, uh, at the very beginning.
보여드린 이 차트는 처음부터 저기 있던 차트예요
Right now it's showing this chart here.
지금은 이 차트를 보여주죠
Uh, and so I've been watching that during the course of the first few weeks of building this, this
이 코스를 만든 첫 몇 주 동안 그걸 지켜봤어요
Uh, and it's been terrific fun.
정말 재미있었어요
Uh, and hopefully you're doing much the same thing, watching the training happening, seeing your
여러분도 같은 일을 하시길 바랍니다 훈련 과정을 지켜보시고 모델
model versions being uploaded to the hub.
버전이 업로드되는 걸 보세요
Uh, and all that remains is for the run to complete.
이제 완주만 하면 돼요
And then tomorrow for us to come and evaluate the model and see how we have done fine tuning our own
내일은 모델을 평가하고 수직화 모델을 어떻게 조정했는지 볼
verticalized model.
거예요
Um, but we'll just wrap up for today.
오늘은 여기까지 하죠
Back to the slides.
슬라이드로 돌아가죠